I
will press the stopwatch
and get ourselves started.
The first thing we're going to do is we're calling to order the Board of Selectmen Special Meeting for Thursday, 06/24/2021.
The first thing we're going do is do the Pledge of Allegiance.
I pledge allegiance
to the flag
>> of The United States.
To
the Republic
for which it stands,
one nation,
under God,
indivisible,
liberty,
>> justice for all. All right, thank you very much.
And we're gonna get started right now with public speak. So Mike Palazzi and Kathy Palazzi, you were first on the meeting. So you're up first.
No we're okay right now. You're okay? Right. Liz
Loecki.
>> Hope I said Loecki. I'm going set the record straight. Sure. It's low
catch.
Low catch. Like my husband explained to me the night we met.
>> It's like catching the ball low. Low catch. Low catch. I, you know, I I will absolutely remember that one.
>> Yeah, I,
yep, I don't have anything for this, moment but thank you. Thank you very much.
Diane Greiner. I'm
all set. I'm a happy buckaroo. Thank you.
The Stanleys.
We're, we're okay. Okay, all right.
Kimberly Prasad.
I'm all set right now, thank you.
Okay.
Kathleen Barrett.
All set, thank you.
Melissa
Kilquist.
Not at this time, thank you.
>> Diane Choquette.
I'm all set, thanks. All right, thank you.
Oh my God, I have to stop the stopwatch, hold on.
I didn't even catch you there.
All right, so 203.
Linda.
Little fish, okay. You're okay? Yep.
Sarah Warnier.
All set now, thank you. Okay, Louise Goodwin.
Okay, Jerry. All set, Jeff, thanks. Yep, Joanne Ebert.
>> One quick comment.
I just wanted to mention that a lot of people seem to think that when
the budget gets cut,
any of them, you know, with the problem that we're having with getting a budget
passed,
that somehow the teachers won't be paid or contracted salaries won't be paid.
And unfortunately we didn't educate anybody last night. I know the superintendent was asked, well, what's going to happen with the salaries?
That's the largest part of the budget, but it's definitely
going to be covered because I don't have the exact percentage,
but I think the cuts would unfortunately,
you know, come from other areas.
So it'd be nice for the public and for us to all get educated that of course the teacher salaries and benefits will be paid.
Thank you.
>> Okay.
Gerald Creme and
Anne Creme because I know you're on there.
>> All right, no comment at this time. Thank you for calling on me. No problem. Or us. Nothing,
okay. And Valerie Bruno.
I'm all set, Jeff, thank you. Okay.
>> Sheri,
I believe you'll participate in our meeting when necessary and Eric is on there. Did I miss anyone? There's a phone number.
>> I don't know. They're unmuted.
If you're calling in on a phone, can you
tell us who you are and if you're participating in public speak
Dennis O'Brien.
Ah Mr. O'Brien okay
I'm all set so far.
>> You got it. Thank you, Dennis.
Okay, our
first item on the agenda,
we cannot do add and deletes, is discuss and act upon the
Board of Finance recommendations for setting the mill rate for twenty twenty one-twenty twenty two.
Eric and Sherri, could you just explain to us what the
current procedure is for this?
>> Sure.
In absence of having a budget on July 1,
the Board of Selectmen is empowered
to, by charter and state law, to set a mill rate. Therefore, we can collect taxes and have the smooth running of the town government.
>> Okay, and what is the recommended, the Board of Finance recommended
mill rate?
>> The Board of Finance did not actually motion
a particular
mill rate to suggest to you at this meeting.
However, the mill rate for the budget
that they pushed
to the next town meeting
would be 35.88
mills,
which equates to a total budget of $12,427,430
>> They really did suggest that last night.
They suggested what? 35.88.
Well,
they agreed
to a
>> budget. That's the only mill rate that was brought up.
>> Correct. But they didn't actually, they motioned
and that motion failed. So they didn't officially motion
to recommend that to you if I'm Officially,
recommended that to the Board. But
>> can
you clarify that, Scott? Because Scott is saying one thing and you're saying another.
So they made a motion to recommend
the 3,588
and it failed?
>> So no, there was a lot of discussion on the Board of Finance about whether they wanted to set it there or whether they wanted to set it higher
or split the difference between this recommendation
and what they previously sent to referendum.
I suggested that one thing they could do is simply round it off
to an even 36
mills,
which would give them basically about $30,000
of leeway.
They made a motion to that effect.
The motion was basically a tie vote because Mark Brinker was not there. So it was a three-three vote, which fails.
And then they did not remotion
to set it at 35.88
mills.
So in effect, there was no legal motion,
but it's only a recommendation to the board anyway.
It's ultimately the board of selectman's decision
to either set a mill rate or I guess not set a mill rate. What was last year's mill rate?
Think it was 35.61.
Hang on, two secs and I'll tell you.
Correct, thirty five point six thirty five point six one, yes. Yep.
>> Well,
our total dollars
that we're looking to raise from taxation is
based upon what's currently going on is not increasing, is it?
>> Yes, because you're not using
funds
the balance to offset. What was the one that we just sent that failed? What was that mill rate?
>> I
don't know off the top of my head. It
was over 36.
I want to say it was 36.2,
36.5
something like that.
It was just under a mil increase
if I remember right. No, was just over a mil increase.
So it would have been 36.6
something.
>> $6.07, okay.
That's what we're seeing in the chat.
And
Sherry,
if I'm correct, you had said that it's better for us to be over than under in the discussion.
Yeah.
Is that correct? That is correct. Okay. Could you explain the mechanism for that for for those of us that, you know, in case there's people listening or watching this as to why we might wanna be over versus under?
>> Well,
we're not sure which way the vote's gonna go. That
would certainly cover us
either
way.
And then
>> so so is it easier to is it easier to refund than it is to send out a supplemental? Is that what you're saying? Yes.
>> Okay. We don't
per state law and per
legal precedent,
the town, if it was a small enough difference, wouldn't actually have to do a refund
because
we can just make it up to the taxpayer, basically refund them in the following year's tax bill,
which is what's normally done if it's not a large amount.
If you guess under and you have to send a supplemental,
that costs the town about $4,500
to reprocess
and to send out new tax bills. So if you guess over, it's free.
If you guess under, it has a potential of costing you $4,500
>> I wouldn't say free, Eric. We do live in a farming community. They have pitchforks.
So you might want to refund them.
Just saying.
>> Well,
we're going to sit there and
the reason why I was asking about last year's number, and it obviously won't work
Is leave it the same, right? Our assessed value went up. Our total assessment went up by what number, Eric
or Sherry? I don't care which one.
>> Well, the grand list went up from $264,000,000
to $2.71.
So I could do the math on that real quick if you want. It's not enough. 3%.
Yeah, it's
3% increase. That's
right.
Yeah, ballpark. Yep.
So,
>> no. Alright. So the issue for us is if they didn't give us a number that they wanted to go to, I mean, I I do believe that we should
we should make the mill rate 36.67
or 36.5,
something in that ballpark. We may as well be over depending upon where we Yeah, don't,
Jeff, that is way over.
It
is.
>> What do you want? So, if you want to sit there and you want to come back to last year's number. I am gonna do something that I never do. You're welcome. And I'm gonna say that I agree with Eric that 30 six is the correct number.
I would say the same thing.
Woah.
>> Can't believe the two of us are agreeing on this so early.
Yeah,
>> exactly. This is a good night. I'm willing to understand that. So, okay. So,
wanted to go high and we now come to the middle. We're
high but we're minuscule high
and hopefully
we're on the right side. High enough. As
>> long as you're high enough to cover what ends up coming down the road, I'm okay with it.
>> Sheri, what do you think, Sheri? Do you think that's enough wiggle room? I think so.
Okay.
Yeah.
Round it off.
Right. 358836.
>> Does anyone want to make a motion to that one?
>> I will make the motion that the town set
the mill rate at 36
mills
for the coming fiscal year
to be addressed or adjusted
according to budget referendums as needed.
I'll second.
>> Scott was supposed to second that, but that's okay. We'll let you do it.
Paula wants in on the action. Thanks,
Thanks,
Paula.
Right. Any further discussion on that number?
No, I
>> think it's a good number. All right. All those in favor,
aye. All those opposed,
all those with an extension,
we'll move on. All right.
The next issue is four, discuss and act upon other Board of Finance recommendations.
I know at the meeting yesterday, there was some discussion about federal
COVID aid that is being sent
to the town. I'd like to discuss that openly
in front of everybody.
Eric, explain again, just so everybody understands the total dollars that the COVID relief money is potentially
coming to the town.
>> As far as we know currently,
the town will get two allotments that will each be
$478,000
>> Okay, 478,000
times two.
So basically,
you're getting pretty close to
$958,000
or $956,000
federal. For
>> clarification, we have not received any of that, right? No, none.
>> Let's be clear. Let me be clear my position so everybody can understand it. That money is COVID relief. That is not supposed to be utilized to offset taxes.
We have to make use of those dollars
in accordance with the regulations that are out there. Discussions that I've had with other people on this call,
I do not expect any of those dollars to be used to offset any items that are out there that are currently under taxation.
So there's been recommendations
that AIM might be used to be offset those costs.
I personally, as one vote on this board, do not believe that that is the right use of those funds.
The right use of those funds is in accordance with the outline that they're there. And if I had my way, I would use them on some capital project
that we as a board or future boards are going to come back to the taxpayers
and ask for money, such as culverts and such as even
if you wanted to extend it out to
building the community center. I would have zero problem with that. I have an incredible problem with people
and residents looking for those dollars to offset structural problems in other areas.
So, to me, there's no sense in talking about those dollars
as a way to offset
operational
problems that if not corrected,
whether they're town or whether educational
persist.
So, that's my opinion. I've expressed that before to other members of the board. I've expressed that to the town administrator.
So,
I want the residents to understand that those dollars are
monies that are great, they're fabulous, that we have the opportunity to receive those. But
if I had my way and it was only my decision, we would be utilizing those dollars to improve the culverts in our community because this board or other boards are going to come back to the residents and ask for not just 900 and some odd thousand dollars to fix those, but millions of dollars to potentially fix those down the road. So I'll second that, Jeff McGuire.
Yeah. Thank you. So
>> I've got a lot of questions and I've been kind of putting a lot of thought into this because
I didn't take
the time to look at the document. I know that I believe Adrian looked at the document,
Eric looked at the document, Diane's looked at the document,
Jeff Murray's looked at the document. So I just have a bunch of questions tonight that maybe we've kind of gone over in the past, but I think to wrap my brain around it and I've been getting a lot of questions that I don't know how to answer some of this so
bear with me if it's stuff that we've already talked about but it's good to
talk again because I want to make sure I understand.
So
I think I don't know if Adrian said or Jeff said we haven't gotten the money yet. So is the concern
that we don't want to, we haven't gotten the money yet because are we putting the town at risk or what's
the what's concern around that?
>> They
just haven't sent us the money yet.
We'll have the money when they send it.
It's
nothing on us.
We've
done the paperwork to get the money.
They just, the state physically has to do a electronic transfer
and put $478,000
in our bank account.
>> Well, but to be clear, the state changes its mind on things all the time. And although these are federal dollars,
that doesn't mean that they can't rejiggle the way that they feel that
they're being allotted.
And so just like they do with ECS money,
and they tie that up in a budget fight, they can do the same thing with this. So you could, you could theoretically try to use this even
forget about the school for a second. If you just talk about saying we want to use this on a town project, right? Or a town thing.
Until we have the money in the bank,
aligning that to anything is a bad idea. Because until you have it, you don't know you have it with the state of Connecticut.
And I think every person that has lived in the state for any length of time would agree on that. You know, you wait until that money's in the bank, and you know, it's yours, before you even start spending it.
I think it would be just a disaster for us to to plan on something and then the state decides to hold it or jiggle it or whatever, you know?
It's it's just Connecticut unfortunately.
So.
I would have Sorry,
>> go ahead, Eric. I was gonna say I would agree
to be somewhat skeptical
about the second tranche of money.
Because certainly there's a discussion at the federal level
about taking some of that money back to fund some of the greater infrastructure.
But I would be fairly confident that we'll end up getting the first
tranche,
you know, or first 470,000,
but it is not in our bank account.
I'm
not telling you it's there, it's not.
Does
that answer that question, Paula?
Yeah,
>> it's not there because we just asked for the money last week by 05:00
on Wednesday.
And
we did what we were instructed
to do right
On the website.
And when I talked to Martin today, who was from OPM,
he said they're just waiting for the US Treasury
to give them the money so they can
>> transfer the money to all the districts. Right. But they don't know when the Treasury is going to give it to them either.
>> No,
no, we don't know, you know, a lot of things,
you know, but I'm just telling you what
I was asked to do and I did everything. I filed everything appropriately.
Listen, and and we appreciate. I have no reason. On top of that. We're gonna get the money. Reasons to believe that we won't get that first trench. Yeah. We're gonna get the. Eric's right. Eric's right with the second trench, they absolutely could pull it back
or adjust it or do anything they want with it. Right. Well, I think the first trench we can
safely say that we're going to get that. It's just a matter of when,
what day.
>> Pardon me for being a pessimist,
but, you know, I like
most people, including yourself, I've lived in Connecticut long enough to question everything until I see it.
Okay.
>> So we Thank you for getting the paperwork done and in on time and all that. Mean, that's always step one with all of this stuff, so Doctor. Yes, it is. Doctor. Anyway,
>> issue is, Paula, that we will get the money. The
mechanism to decide how to spend it is the next question.
Right. Yeah,
>> that was my next question, but finish your thought. No, that's the next question. We're going to get this money.
Number one, and I'll go to Adrian because, and Eric,
from all my understanding, we cannot use this money to offset taxation.
Yes or no?
You cannot.
Eric?
I think there's some gray area.
>> Gray area and everything. That's absolutely the truth. But the basics of this is not to offset taxation. If we sit there and as a board decide to use this to offset taxation, we're setting ourselves up for a huge future problem. It's
just not
>> The
the goal
funds
was to
very specifically
encourage towns to spend money,
to spend this money and that's why there's a time limit on how long it can be how long it has to be spent with them.
It's to get the economy back up and running.
And so
the bill and guidelines,
if you actually go through the document are very much geared
towards new initiatives.
It's not to fund your old initiatives.
You know, it's, it's, it's to build new initiatives. So,
you know,
you know, and I and there are a lot of little pet projects, things put in there. So like,
you know, there are some things in there, Erica has looked at as far as infrastructure,
specifically related to
water courses and
water, you know, public water systems. Know, But most of that public water stuff was put in there to benefit cities and towns that have water and structural issues. In fact, if anyone read the River East, there was a, you know, there was some conversation about, you know, Portland's having some issue with their water.
And they're hoping to use a bunch of that money to update their infrastructure as a new project initiative and help pay for it. But
it was even designed for bigger cities like Detroit
is still struggling with lead in their water. So one of the whole reason the water system stuff was put in there was to allow Detroit to use a bunch of this money,
you know, as it comes in to help upgrade theirs.
So we're gonna, we're gonna be struggling even for the idea of using it for co verts. That may be something that's a, you know, we may not qualify for. Well, you actually have to go through and do a bunch of EPA stuff
to qualify for that covert stuff. So there's a lot of hoops to jump through no matter what you decide to use it for.
>> How
come
in previous
meetings or conversations,
is it an interpretation thing when somebody's reading the document? Some people are saying
the document is lenient
and then other people are saying it's not as lenient and what you can use it for. Is it, do you think, what are you, what is everybody's thoughts? I mean,
like I said, I haven't looked through it thoroughly,
but it's just very confusing
when someone's saying it's lenient and then someone else is saying that's not lenient.
Isn't everything the federal government does confusing?
>> Can I answer that? It's Diane Choquette because I read all this stuff.
Please, Diane. So I'll just tell you everybody's looking at press releases and fact sheets.
Okay, those are high level executive summary documents
designed to give you a framework.
You really have to read the regulation to know all the hoops you have to jump through to be an eligible
spend for that project.
So you have to do the work to read the regulation.
You probably already signed a document when you applied for the funds that you're going to comply with the treasury regulation
And you're gonna keep all the records and you're gonna do all the reporting because that was part of the requirements.
>> You Hang on Diane, was that the case, Sherry, that we had to apply and sign something?
>> Yeah.
And we have to, in any
situation like this, when you draw down money from the federal government, you have to agree to the conditions that
they
set forth.
So it's an old procedure.
>> So, you know, does everybody have to read the, you know, Treasury regulation?
It's 137
pages in a PDF. It's long. It's boring.
You know, should a group of people read it and do an executive summary for people may be a good idea, you know, to get the facts out because there's a lot of conditions in that regulation
and you have to take the conditions and apply them to our situation
>> in order to figure out what you could spend the money on. And not for nothing, Diane, if you don't mind, is it okay if I tell people what you did before you retired and came and got more involved? Yeah, can do that. I read treasury regulations and implemented them for banks. So her background is literally doing this type of stuff and making sure banks were in compliance when they dealt with the treasury. So I
that's why I'm I'm, you know, when Diane says that, you know, we had a concern about how this stuff was spent, I took the time to read the regulations.
You know, Jeff Murray also took the time to read them and I
concur with what she was finding. So,
it's a little more involved
than I think people
>> were saying. So. I mean, we'll just have to do our legwork and our due diligence on this to make the right decisions. That's also be a little bit of work.
Right.
>> Did I understand I was on the board of finance call last night and I don't know who brought it up. It was either maybe it was a conversation between Diane and Sherry. I thought somebody said there was a contact
that you can ask questions to.
Is that did I hear that right? And
>> I called him today,
Martin half, which is the one that has been
forwarding all the documents to me
and he's from opm he said opm cannot help us.
They are just a minute administering
the documents and everything from the US Treasury. Right. If you have particular
questions or
want their approval cannot for something,
you have to contact them, the US Treasury, and put it in writing.
And they will render a decision.
>> My experience on working with the Treasury,
so they will always give you contact information.
You are going to call in there, you're going to email somebody,
and they're going to cite you the section of the regulation to go read.
That's all they'll do for you. They're not going to opine on anything for you. So if you want a legal opinion, you're going to have to hire an attorney, which is a lot of money. So,
but I think there's enough in that regulation for us to figure out how it applies to us, and then get the information then make decisions from there. There's just a little bit of legwork to do. But the key and
>> reading through the document is that the bulk of it is focused on new initiatives specifically,
right? Yes. That's what their goal is. Their goal is to get you to do things that maybe otherwise wouldn't have done
and implement them. And it's really a lot of it is written to bigger suburban districts,
but certainly we can find areas to work with it here within the town.
You know, for instance, one of the conversations we've been having is, you know, whether or not it's a possibility to use those funds to
bring the community center to fruition,
right? Because it is a new initiative.
It is not something that is currently involved in taxes. So
it's not, we're not lowering taxes by doing that, we're not offsetting taxes by doing that.
So we may be able to use some of those funds for helping to build the community center because that really fits in the crux of what this bill was, which is how to serve
areas of a community which are currently not being served right now. Right? And so that would actually serve the whole community,
you know, and it will allow us to do some things that we're not currently doing, bringing in state resources,
for both,
you know, the kids
know, and for the seniors by having a fixed location.
And if we were able to do some of this, it may allow us to take some of the money we have currently put away
and use that to help offset bringing in a community services director,
you know, for a couple of years, so that we could have not just a building, but someone to functionally
make that building more efficient for this community.
You know, whether it's bringing in all the outside resources that we haven't had spaces for. I mean there are programs for
bringing in people to help do taxes, bringing in a dental clinic, bringing in a health screening clinic,
know bringing in you know other kid programs and working with and
working with cool and some other bigger, bigger, higher level stuff that we don't have dedicated space for,
that once that building is up, we will.
So being able to look at
benefiting the whole community by doing that is something that we're really trying to focus on. Currently that the RFP
for the community center is up on the town website.
And we are putting it out to bid to get some numbers to see what that looks like. And that will hopefully give us some direction as to whether or not,
the funds would fall into that category and what we can or can't use for it is sort of the next step. So, I mean, that's just one idea. I know Eric had some ideas also and
so we have some things that are out there that we're working on. We're not just letting it sit, we're actively trying to pursue this.
>> But the decision will be made on what
to spend it on when we got it.
All right, Paula, next question. Just
>> one last question from
off the top of my head. So Eric gave us some recommendations
we're going look at on how to spend the money. Can we
reconsider
other areas once we get the money or are we locked in? Do we have to tell them we're using it for a specific
reason
when they give us the money or can we decide when we get it?
>> The way that I understand it is we can decide whatever we want to do with it.
We just have to present it, and Sherri would know from the submission standpoint.
We're going to have to submit to the federal government that this is how we decided to spend it, and then they're gonna evaluate that and determine if it falls within their guidelines.
>> Yeah. There'll be reporting requirements that we will get notification
of
once we determine how to spend the money that we have to fill out those reports and send them in.
I believe
they're going to be a quarterly basis.
>> For
us, the first report will be due 10/01/2021.
We have for now until October to figure out what we're going do with the money. Yeah, we don't have anything in writing yet, but yeah,
>> absolutely. We don't even have to spend that. What is the timeline for spending the money?
First tranche is what, two years?
>> Three years. Think if you were building a project, can go out to 2026,
but I think that's for big projects. Right.
>> Okay.
All right. Any other questions, Paula, related to that? Does that answer your question, Paula?
Yes.
Yes, yes, yes. Thank you.
>> Do we have anything else that we want to discuss related to the Board of Finance and the recommendations they had at last night's meeting?
Okay. Then we have Item five,
which is an executive session for the town administrators
and review. Does anyone have
>> a problem if I allow public speak before we do that? No, I think it'd be appropriate because we don't know how long we're going to be an executive.
>> All right.
So let's go through this again, Kathy and Mike Pelosi.
No? No, we're all set. Thank you. Thank you.
Liz Loquetch.
Yeah,
I got
do.
>> Just wanna throw this out there. What about
business development or something
for
COVID money,
try to bring new business into the town, whatever might be necessary to try to get something going in this town so that
we poor taxpayers are not the only one paying this bill.
Just a thought.
All right, thank you. Diane
Greiner.
>> I'm all set. Thank you. All right, the Stanleys.
I have a question about why
>> we don't know what the actual budget vote was.
We got the same thing saying you're doing it again next week and there's and that there was a recount
that I couldn't find any place that actually said what the vote was and I'm curious about that.
>> Eric, do you have the recount stuff from Carol? Otherwise, I can try to find it. Yeah.
Give me two seconds.
>> The biggest thing I think needs to be said about the whole reason we went into recount is,
we apparently had a tape that needed to be changed on one of the
tabulators, And so when it printed out, it was really
hard to read the numbers. And so someone
misread the numbers and put them up accordingly.
Was really good. Because I never I looked all over the place and I couldn't find the numbers. So there were some numbers posted on Facebook and then because I think we went into a recount I mean, what was posted on Facebook was preliminary.
Once they decided to do a recount, it makes no sense to put up the numbers because those are not certified.
Until they did finish the recount and they were certified,
really it's not appropriate to put numbers up. I mean, to be honest, putting numbers up early in this case actually caused a problem because they weren't correct and it was it was a human error.
Some of it human error on the part of the the you know, with the the tape, but also some of it was human error in the way that some people filled out the ballots instead of filling in the the circle. They made a circle around it. If the circle happened to go through the
through where the oval was, then it counted it. But if they missed it, it didn't count it. Eric, do you have the numbers?
>> Yes.
The June 22 budget referendum
final results
to 95 voted yes.
Three eighty seven voted no
for ballots had blanks.
You know, so there's a slight difference between when the machine tabulated
a blank
and when people tabulated a blank because when the registrars
look at something where it's clearly circled,
they call that
circled the yes. But if the machine does not see anything in the oval, it does not call it a yes.
So that was the final result. There were six eighty six votes.
It was absolutely
my fault for
issuing the first incorrect
vote total.
And I apologize for that. It was late at night.
I mean, did the math wrong. Okay, but to be fair,
>> that
printout was extremely light and when they looked at it, realized what the issue was.
>> So we can answer the Stanley's question directly. Can you give them the other five questions and just put it out there on this meeting?
Those numbers did not change.
>> Okay, they haven't been posted, then they can't see it. Yeah, I'm sorry, Jeff, you're correct.
>> Okay,
so what do you want me to do? Advisory
questions can you give those totals please?
>> Honestly I only have the machine print out.
I do not have
the
I can pull it up. You know what, but I know the what I put out before
for a document was correct.
So
yeah for that.
I will talk you through it.
So non binding question number one, is the elementary school budget
too high or too low?
Too high was $4.25,
too low was 160,
and the rest
were blanks.
On the question,
is the Andover budget
too high,
$3.19,
too low, 199.
On the answer, should the resident state trooper program be eliminated?
Yes,
two twelve,
no,
four forty five.
Question number four, should the Andover Elementary School and town budgets be voted on separately?
Yes, four twenty one.
No,
two twenty four.
>> Those were the results. And those included a total of 18 absentee ballots, by the way.
18 absentee ballots.
>> Correct.
That does not include the several
of the ballots
samples
that got mailed to people's houses
announcing that there was a vote coming up where people just filled out the sample ballot that they were given and returned that to the town. Those do not count.
>> Okay.
Did that answer your question? Yes, it did. Thank you. Sorry
about that. We'll try to get that posted up in the future so that you can see those results.
Kimberly Persong?
Nothing right now. Thank you. Okay.
We have a phone number that ends in 3529.
Oh, no comment right now. Thank you.
Dennis O'Brien, I'm going to skip you.
Melissa
Kalkwist.
>> Yes, I have my husband here, Derek, who would like to speak.
>> I believe Carl last night at the
finance meeting
brought up that he would like to see transparency
and what what you guys are spending it on and I think that's a great idea.
Okay,
thank you very much.
Diane Choquette.
>> No comment, just I will volunteer my time if you need any assistance in
researching the regulations and anything on this or putting together an executive summary.
Thank you very much.
Thank you thank
Linda
fish
all set thank you thank you
Sarah Warnier.
All set, thank you.
Louise Goodwin.
All set, thanks.
Joanne Ebert.
>> Think it was important that the last vote we all know it didn't pass
by a lot
and
the Board of Finance did want the feedback from the questions so that was great to have that input.
So I hope that the people that said they were waiting for the input, certain individuals,
you know, will take that to heart. I don't know if that's going to happen.
And
just,
I want to make sure that we can believe in our leaders And one of our leaders was asked a question last night and that's why I'm making this point twice because I think it's really important because I know it and I want our leader to present it to the audience whether it reflects
good or bad on what she wants to happen. But when it was asked you know what's going to happen with the contracts what's going to happen with the salaries
you know it wasn't brought up of course there's going to be a cut to the budget when one of the questions
you know is so
you know in order to get past that they want to see some cuts you know just like it's been talking about so I just want to make sure that
I want her to say of course the salaries will be paid in contracts that's the biggest part of the budget but we've never let that I just was so shocked that that wasn't talked about. Other things would have to be cut, but not the
for salaries.
Thanks.
>> All right. Thank you. Gerald Cremay
and Anne Cremay, I'm sorry. Thank
you for the opportunity for being there for us.
>> All right, thank you for all you do, Jerry.
Marcy Miner.
>> Hi, I
just want to say the last town meeting that we had, I really was impressed with how well
it was ran even though it was still,
there were still some problems, but I felt like it was a lot better.
Thank you Jeff for making sure that people
behaved and Paula. I thought you did a pretty good job at moderating. I know it's really difficult
and
I just one thing that I'm thinking about when I'm thinking about the meeting coming up is.
You know everyone's
concerned about
passing it at town meeting and not at referendum
and one of the things that bothered me was having a hand vote for everything.
And I feel like if we did
for all the votes, we, you know, did those by ballot,
we might be, it might work a little better. I don't know. That's my thought. I prefer that all the votes were done by ballot.
Eric, you had some input on that? Sure,
>> you as a member of the public
can request
any
motion,
any,
the
members of the public are not obligated
to vote
via hand
if you choose and a significant fraction of the population
wants to vote by secret ballot,
that is what would happen. But you in the audience have to request that for a measure.
Dennis, am I correct in that?
>> Yes, that's right. According to Robert's rules,
you know, the the the norm is to vote by
either standing or raising hands,
but a motion for a secret ballot can be made. And if it passes by a majority vote, that's what happens.
>> Yeah. You just basically have to ask to move the motion to paper ballot.
Okay. Correct. Thank you.
Okay. Kathleen Barrett.
>> Hi,
thanks for
giving me the chance to listen in and participate.
I would comment that
I really appreciated
the opportunity
as a voter
to be able to
express my preferences
in a way that felt
comfortable
through
the
ballot questions on the referendum.
So
I
commend you for
inviting that kind of opinion
of the voters
I would be glad for more opportunities
for that
And I hope you all
take
really seriously as you take your next steps
what kind of opinions the voters expressed
to the best of your ability.
So thank you.
Thank you for voting.
You're welcome.
Erin Boris?
No comment. Thank you.
And Caitlin McIntosh.
It all started. Thank you. All
>> right. Valerie Bruno is last. Would you like to comment or add anything to our meeting? Yes, thank you. I know Ms. Hebert said that I didn't answer a question last night. So I do want to be clear. The question was asked,
what happens if the budget's not passed with the school?
That was the question that was posed last night. And the answer was that we continued
with the existing budget
that everybody would still be getting paid.
That was the question that was asked was what we do if the budgets not passed.
As for the conversation tonight,
I do have to speak on behalf of the school
after,
you know,
the decision was made to cut 97,000
and move forward to the town meeting.
It is very disappointing
that the whole million would be hoarded for optional
projects
and after
a variety of people, including Mr Mandeville
had expected
staff to be cut at AES and that conversation had been going on since January
to now tonight here that the plan for the $478,000
is to finish the community center and potentially hire a director
is very difficult.
And I think it's going to be very difficult for parents
moving forward on Tuesday as well to hear that that money would be hoarded solely for optional projects and that there would be absolutely no consideration of the $97,000
that
was cut. Well, to be clear, Valerie. Adrian,
>> point of order, it's public speak. Yeah. Let's let it finish.
All right, let's go.
Valerie, continue, please.
>> So I think that it's not an issue of people wanting to drag this out and wanting to vote no on Tuesday. I just think that as many people tonight have said, there are a variety of people in this community and we need to consider all of the voters. And there were voters that said the school budget was too high and there were voters that said the town budget was too high.
And as a result of last night and tonight,
the school is what's getting cut 97,000
and the town has been given $478,000
for two years
and for it to result in the conversation being let's hire director and finish the community center, that's going to be a very, very difficult thing for people to accept.
Thank you.
Adrian, would you like to Jeff,
>> my name was mentioned and also
she just gave false information and so I'm kind of we need to address these things as they come up. The town budget has also been cut by the Board of Finance.
Eric, what was the actual number last night? I'm sorry, didn't stay on the whole call.
With extra money coming in though, Adrian. Valerie.
>> I listen, both of you. Stop it. No, how much was the town budget cut, Eric?
Thousand dollars So the town budget was cut 50,000
and the school budget was cut $97,000
Now let's have an actual conversation about how much money the school had. They had $186,000
on May 12 to decide what they wanted to spend on.
You still have $54,000
>> in leftover COVID funds from that alignment. We don't have that money, Adrienne. You made it a point earlier to say money in hand. That money is not in hand. You have $54,000
No. In We do not have $54,000
>> in our account. I'm sorry. So on the May 12 meeting, you gave incorrect information because you said you have meeting discussed
>> Excuse me. I'm done with I'm done with this. But you did have a $136,000
Adrian, excuse me. Excuse me. Pound money.
You two would like to if you two would like to have a conversation after this meeting, I that seems appropriate to me. But to sit there and do this on right now The problem is my frustration Jeff is that we keep having these conversations come up in public meetings and no one addresses the fact that they had $136,000
>> in leftover money and they've decided to spend it on other projects. They weren't worried about this year's budget. They were worried about spending it on other things. So it's disingenuous for them. They still have $54,000
in COVID funds. If they're not in their account yet, that's fine. But they have allotted to spend it for stuff.
So they have $186,000
but now they're saying oh we want the town money too and I don't think that's fair to the town and it's disingenuous for them to come after the town funds when they've spent their money already
that it's wrong
If they were worried about this year's budget, then maybe they should have addressed that with that extra funds or come to the Board of Finance, which has been very reasonable over the years and said, hey, we're worried about adjusting our budget as we go forward. Can we ask for that money to be transferred into next year or rolled over? And they didn't do that. Instead, they decided to spend it. And now they're coming after town funds to fill in the gap. That's not right. All right. I have a problem with it. Okay, understood.
>> And thank you. So Valerie, thank you very much. Appreciate your time.
Is there anyone else that I missed for public speak?
Okay.
Paula, I'm
gonna make a motion that we go into executive session right now. So if you could,
everyone, thank you for attending. I appreciate your time.
Thank you.
>> Hey, are we
we going in? Are we going to No, you still got Liz. Session with without Eric first and then we're going to invite him in. Yeah, you still got to get Liz and a couple others off Eric, the
>> you hear me out? Yeah, if you can, we're going to just sit there and quickly do this and then we'll bring you right back in. It won't be very long. Yeah, give us fifteen minutes or so, Eric. Yeah, go have a snack. We'll text you. Go have a Wally break, a cigarette break.
Hang on, guys.
Are we leaving Dennis on?
>> Don't think Dennis needs to participate. Don't think did. Did you turn the recording off?
>> Yes. Not yet. You have to make a motion for it. Who's that last number?
Dennis.
>> But you have to make your motion to go. I did. I made a motion to go on executive session. I'll second it. Second that. All right. It is 752.
Okay. I'm gonna stop.
Recording?
Yep.